Guide to the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection, 2012-2020 RL.11067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection
2012-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Dept. of Art, Art History, and Visual Studies
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11067
27.5 Linear Feet 37 boxes; 1 oversize folder
784.5 Gigabytes Electronic files
The Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Art degree program at Duke University has been awarded since 2013. Collection contains masters theses submitted by graduates of the program. Written theses formats include typescripts, handmade books, zines, digital video, and audio files. Creative theses portfolios include three-dimensional artwork or artifacts such as boxes; printed photobooks; color and black-and-white photographic prints; digital still images; digital film, audio, and video; and images and film of objects, multi-media performances, and exhibits. Subjects range widely: they include U.S. and Southern cultures; world cultures; street photography; environmental narratives and documentaries; city and rural communities; themes of social justice, memory, and identity; women and spirituality; and abstract constructs. Other countries and regions represented include China, Vietnam, and the Middle East. Submission of work to the archival project is voluntary. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into series by MFA program year. Within these series, MFA theses are separated into two types: written and creative. Within those two groups, authors are listed in alphabetical order by last name. Many authors have entries in both groups. Author abstracts and artists' statements are included when available.
Biographical / Historical
First awarded in the 2012-2013 academic year, the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Art degree program at Duke University brings together two forms of artistic activity - the documentary approach and experimental production in analog, digital, and computational media - fostering collaborations across disciplines and media.
The philosophy of the program is guided by a belief in the intersection of personal artistic work with interpretive knowledge and of the relevance of the individual documentary or experimental artist within the cultural history and life of communities. A key component to the program is the notion of creative engagement through the arts and the role of the artist in society. Graduates are expected to generate work that has impact both within and outside the academy.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of the magic lantern apparatus in the Mao Wei thesis project is restricted unless with supervision by ADA Curator or other library staff. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Electronic files have been migrated to a library server and are open for research; they may be accessed in the Rubenstein Library reading room only. Original carriers such as hard drives and optical discs are closed to use.
Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, but some donors have outlined specific restrictions regarding the use of their work.
Provenance
The Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2015 and as gifts from 2016-2020.
Collection Overview
Collection contains masters theses submitted each year by graduates of Duke University's Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts program (MFA/EDA), beginning with 2015.
The collection is arranged by program year, then in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses. Written theses exist in both analog and electronic form; many include handmade books, digital video, or audio files. Creative portfolios include three-dimensional artwork or artifacts; photobooks; color and black-and-white photographic prints in varying sizes; digital still images; digital film, audio, and video; and images and film of multi-media performances and exhibit installations. Artifacts are sometimes part of the project, including one large magic lantern apparatus.
Themes range widely, and include U.S. and Southern cultures; cultures around the world; street photography; environmental narratives and documentaries; city and rural communities; social justice, memory, segregation, and identity; and abstract constructs. Most projects are based in the United States, but some are centered on Middle Eastern, Southeast Asian or Chinese history and culture.
Most authors have contributed both creative and written theses; others have elected to contribute only one or the other. Not all authors have both written and creative theses. Participation in the archival project is voluntary; therefore this archive represents the graduates of the MFA EDA program who submitted their work for inclusion.
African Americans -- Segregation -- Southern States; Culture in art; Endangered species; Documentary films; Feminism -- Italy; Folklore -- American; Genetic disorders; Identity (Psychology); Masculinity -- United States; Nature -- effect of human beings on; Performance art; Photography -- China; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Whites -- Race identity -- United States; Women's rights; Iran -- History; Middle West -- Photographs; Southern States -- Photographs; Southern States -- Social life and customs; Southern States -- Social conditions; United States -- Photographs; Vietnam -- Photographs; United States -- Social conditions; 16mm; Artists' books; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Digital audio formats; Digital images; Digital prints; Digital moving image formats; Experimental films; Film; Gelatin silver prints; Home movies; Inkjet prints; Masters theses; Optical disks; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2013
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains Duke University Master of Fine Arts in Experimental Documentary Arts theses from the class of 2013. The projects are listed in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses, and within are listed in alphabetical order by the students' last names.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic materials in this series have been migrated from original media to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room.
  - Written Theses, 2013
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2013 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - Barstow, Eric, 2013 (Box 1)
      A Family Analysis: The Underlying Logic for A Family Affair
    - Borgeson, Marika, 2013; Audio tracks derived from optical disc. Approximately 0.5 gigabytes. (Box 1, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
      Play Track One: written thesis and audio files meant to accompany written thesis.
    - Brubaker, Philip, 2013 (Box 1)
      Reporting From the Realm of the Unreal
    - Doggett, Laura, 2013 (Box 1)
      Lauren and Amanda
    - Haster, Wolfgang, 2013 (Box 1)
      The Sandcastle
    - Landesberg, Elizabeth, 2013 (Box 1)
      Light Shines Forever
    - Lisignoli, Peter, 2013 (Box 1)
      Distances and Relativities: Reimagining History as Allegory and Archive as Process
    - Manning, Annabel, 2013 (Box 1)
      Out of the Shadows: Undocumented and Unafraid
    - McCarty, Lisa, 2013 (Box 4)
      MDCCCXXXIX, housed in black plastic 3 ring binder box
    - McCubbin, Laurenn, 2013 (Box 1)
      A Monument to the Risen: Emotional Labor, Intimacy and the Spaces of Sex Work
    - Minik, Natalie, 2013 (Box 1)
      Can You Waltz?
    - Mok, Chung Ling Jolene Mok, 2013 (Box 1)
      untitled thesis
    - Sanders, Talena, 2013 (Box 4)
      Untitled thesis. Thesis includes corrugated cardboard underneath last page, packaged with perpendicular strips of 5/8-inch wide film strips that are stapled closed; top page has color reproduction of Liahon, NOVIEMBRE 1951.
    - Wanek, Joel, 2013 (Box 1)
      Breaking With Reality: A Dialogue with Dawoud Bey
  - Creative Theses, 2013
    This subseries contains the creative theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2013. Artists' statements and abstracts are included when provided.
    - McCarty, Lisa, 2013
      Lisa McCarty's MFA thesis MDCCCXXXIX includes 15 20x24" color LightJet prints made from 4x5" film sheet exposed with handmade camera; 8 11x14" matted color LightJet prints made from 120mm negatives; 6 11x14" matted silver gelatin prints; and 1, handmade box camera.
      McCarty provided the following abstract: "MDCCCXXXIX (1839) is a narrative of how photography came about, and how it continues to. In Latent Image: The Discovery of Photography, curator and historian Beaumont Newhall states, "Photography has no single inventor. At the same time, distantly removed from one another, experimenters were working on the same problem unaware of each others work until, in January of 1839, an announcement was made in Paris by the Academie des Sciences of the success of one of them."
      Though the 1839 announcement publicly illuminated the discovery of the method to fix images, experiments to this end have been documented as early as 1802 and have never ceased. Consequently, 1839 is both a fixed date and an idea. It signifies the moment photography was born, though this is a moment that repeats with every generation of imagemakers. With the emergence of every new method for fixing images the medium is reborn, persisting much like a phoenix, cyclically regenerating from its own ashes. Therefore, one could say it is the project of every photographer to reinvent the medium whether by technical, formal, and/or conceptual means.
      MDCCCXXXIX is an account of one such project. My particular experiments have involved pilgrimages to document sites where Fox Talbot, Daguerre, and Niépce worked, reading and generating facsimiles of their instructions for building cameras and fixing images, and finally the creation and systematic testing of my own cameras. Through this process I have discovered photography yet again, and have the pleasure of rediscovering it each and every time I make an image.
      And so, still distantly removed from one another across geographic and temporal expanses, the cycle endures. Experimenters are still working on the same problem and MDCCCXXXIX continues to unfold."
      - Handmade camera, 2013 (Box 6)
      - Kaleidoscope Picture (12:00 -1:00 a.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Bedroom Window (6:55 - 7:07 a.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Flower Arrangement (11:45 - 11:58 a.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Lace (1:35 - 2:13 p.m.), 2012 (Box 9)
      - Lace (2:30 - 2:47 p.m.), 2012 (Box 9)
      - Preserved Butterflies (7:00 - 7:12 p.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Electric Hurricane Lamp (1:00 - 2:00 p.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - The Focal Encyclopedia (7:15 - 7:35 p.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - View from Studio Window (9:08 - 9:09 a.m.), 2012 (Box 9)
      - View from Studio Window (10:47 - 10:48 a.m.), 2012 (Box 9)
      - Filaments (5:00 - 6:00 p.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Filaments (2:08 - 2:09 a.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Ticking Clock (11:00 – 12:00 a.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Flower Arrangement (4:50 - 5:18 a.m.), 2013 (Box 9)
      - Kaleidoscope Picture (12:00 - 12:30 a.m.), 2012 (Box 9)
      - View from the Window at Le Gras (First View), 2012 (Box 7)
      - View from the Window at Le Gras (70 cm), 2012 (Box 7)
      - Oriel Window with Mousetrap Camera, Lacock Abbey, 2011 (Box 7)
      - Boulevard du Temple, Paris (Hommage), 2012 (Box 7)
      - Boulevard du Temple, Paris, (Reflection), 2012 (Box 7)
      - Corridor, Lacock Abbey (Double Exposure), 2011 (Box 7)
      - View through Correspondence, Le Gras (Double Exposure), 2012 (Box 7)
      - View from the Window at Le Gras (Last View), 2011 (Box 7)
      - Facsimile of facsimile of title page to "Notice on Heliography" by Nicéphore Niépce, 2013 (Box 8)
      - Facsimile of facsimile of title page to "A Practical Description of the Process Called The Daguerreotype" by Louis Daguerre, 2013 (Box 8)
      - Facsimile of facsimile of title page to "Some Account of the Art of Photogenic Drawing" by William Henry Fox Talbot, 2013 (Box 8)
      - Facsimile of facsimile of first facsimile of a photograph by William Henry Fox Talbot, 2013 (Box 8)
      - Facsimile of facsimile of "View of Courtyard" by Nicéphore Niépce, 2013 (Box 8)
      - Facsimile of facsimile of "Boulevard Temple" by Louis Daguerre, 2013 (Box 8)
    - Brubaker, Phillip, 2013; Apple Quicktime video file transferred from an external hard drive, approximately 25 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0004)
      Philip Brubaker's MFA thesis film "envisional minds" is a file made from original HD video master.
      Brubaker provided the following abstract: "envisional minds explores the rich inner lives of three children, all of whom profess devotion to an imaginary friend. Catalina, Avery and Averie talk to and interact with their imaginary friends, albeit in different ways. The film alternates between subjective and objective depictions of playtime with imaginary beings."
      Contents: Brubaker_envisionalminds.mov file: Digital video, 22 minutes, audio
    - Sanders, Talena, 2013
      Talena Sanders' multi-part thesis includes 56 digital image files documenting the MFA thesis exhibition. "Return to Virtue" includes 23 images documenting Sanders' installation, "Keep Sweet" includes three images documenting Sanders's performance, and "Dressed in White" includes 30 images documenting Sanders's installation and performance.
      - Keep Sweet, 2013
        Three (3) color digital files documenting the performance Keep Sweet, exhibited at the Power Plant Gallery in Spring 2013 as part of Sanders' MFA thesis exhibition. Images by EB Landesberg. Sanders provided the following abstract:
        "A performance based on interactions with women who were members of the Fundamentalist Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints sect based in Colorado City, AZ and Hildale, UT. Performers were provided with dresses that FLDS women are required to wear in their daily lives and a set of instructions of how to behave as they moved through the MFA thesis exhibition space.
      - Dressed in White, 2013
        Thirty (30) color digital image files documenting the installation and performance Dressed in White, exhibited at the Power Plant Gallery in Spring 2013 as part of Sanders' MFA thesis exhibition. Images by Laurenn McCubbin. Sanders provided the following abstract:
        "This endurance performance explored the textiles imbued with meaning through Mormon marriage rituals. A hand-sewn sculptural object composed of four Mormon gowns used in temple marriage rites was deconstructed dress by dress, then further deconstructed to raw materials over the course of the exhibition. Each dress was deconstructed while on my body, revealing a set of Mormon temple garments underneath. The revelation of the infamous "Mormon magic underwear" demystifies a source of public titillation, while approaching the profane in disclosing something held so sacred to the faithful."
      - Return to Virtue, 2013
        23 color digital image files documenting the exhibition at the Power Plant Gallery as part of Sanders' MFA thesis exhibition in Spring 2013. Sanders included the following abstract:
        "Return to Virtue is a staging of a Mormon teenage girl's fantasy bedroom, examining how material culture displayed in domestic space projects ideals of faith and identity. A Mormon youth's bedroom can become a platform for projecting pious ambition. This extensive collection of Mormon ephemera formed a display of fanatical devotion and desire."
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2014
  Series contains Duke University Master of Fine Arts in Experimental Documentary Arts theses from the class of 2014. The projects are listed in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses, and within are listed in alphabetical order by the students' last names.
  - Written Theses, 2014
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2014 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - A, Runa, 2014 (Box 2)
      The Beginner's Heart
    - Berg, Amanda, 2014 (Box 2)
      Adventures of Storytelling
    - Boillot, Rachel, 2014 (Box 13)
      Written thesis titled "a photograph is a letter is a story." Housed in book-shaped box labeled CHECK REGISTER JOURNAL No. 2, The Hamilton Autographic Register Company and measuring 17 1/2 inches by 13 inches by 3 1/2 inches and including an internal painted wood box measuring 12 1/16 inches by 16 inches by 2 15/16 inches.
    - Burmeister, Brenda, 2014 (Box 2)
      On Letters and Lullabies
    - Chavez, Malina, 2014 (Box 2)
      MotherBoard: Mapping the Personal Political
    - Espelie, Erin, 2014 (Box 2)
      Black-Mirror Moving Image
    - Garrahan, Sarah, 2014 (Box 2)
      fare
    - Kelly, Caitlin Margaret, 2014 (Box 2)
      The Vertigo of Distance
    - Niu, Jing, 2014 (Box 2)
    - Rash, John, 2014 (Box 2)
    - Stratton, Jennifer, 2014 (Box 5)
      Thesis titled "Soil Stories"; title sewn in upper case cursive onto tag attached to string that packages archival/non-archival box, which also contains a small sample of dirt.
    - Shan, Shan, 2014 (Box 2)
      W.R.O.N.G.
  - Creative Theses, 2014
    This subseries contains the creative theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2014. Artists' statements and abstracts are included when provided.
    - Berg, Amanda, 2014
      "Every body hit somebody" is a multi-media project created by Amanda Berg from 2012-2014 that explores the world of women who play football. Fifteen black-and-white images in poster format and a documentary film portray players from the Carolina Phoenix, based in Durham, North Carolina, as they travel across the United States. The posters are on newsprint; folded, they measure 8 3/4 x 11 3/8 inches; unfolded, they measure 22 3/4 x 35 inches. Please handle carefully.
      From the artist's abstract: "'There's a piece of yourself you can express on the football field... It is so emancipating, it's indescribable.' (#27 Tamara Jarrett, LB/TE) 'Every Body Hit Somebody' explores issues and expectations around gender, identity, and equality through the documentation of the Carolina Phoenix, a semi-professional women's tackle football team based in Durham, North Carolina."
      "Still photographs comprise the backbone of a corresponding film. Accounts from players on the team and observations of them throughout their 2013 season testify to their strength and resilience in the face of barriers still imposed on women."
      "The 43-minute documentary film is constructed from archival media combined with 16mm film, still photographs, and photo-elicitation interviews. It is edited in a formal structure inspired by chapter XIX in Adventures of Ideas by Alfred North Whitehead. The corresponding still photographs chronologically document the Carolina Phoenix on and off the field during their 2013 championship season. The photographs were reproduced on newsprint to visually underscore the relationship between American football, masculinity, and mass media culture. The prints were then used to facilitate a public forum around issues of gender identity and empowerment."
      Biography
      Amanda Berg is a documentary photographer and filmmaker who combines conventional and experimental approaches to nonfiction storytelling in search of shared experiences. Her work tends to explore themes of identity formation, gender equality, and togetherness in America. She has worked as a newspaper photographer, documentary arts educator, and tennis coach, among other things. Amanda holds a BFA in Photojournalism from Rochester Institute of Technology and a MFA in Experimental and Documentary Arts from Duke University.
      - Newsprint posters, 2012-2014, 30 newsprint posters (Box 19)
        One set of 15 posters is designated for public access; another preservation set of 15 posters is closed to general use.
      - Every Body Hit Somebody documentary film (43 minutes), 2014, Video file (Apple Pro Res format) and still images (JPEG format); approximately 49 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0013)
    - Boillot, Rachel, 2014, 46 items 1 box 46 color inkjet prints 20 1/4 x 24 1/4 inches; All photographs are scanned 4x5 or 120 format color negatives, shot 2012-2013, and printed on Museo Silver Rag in 2016. (Box 14)
      The 46 color prints in "Post Script," taken in 2012-2013, portray the exteriors and interiors of small post offices and the people connected with them, in rural Southern states such as Kentucky, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, and Tennessee. Selected text from the photographer's abstract: "The post office serves as town center in rural communities. Often acting as a town's sole address, this location embodies the numerical identity of place. Without its presence in the landscape, a ZIP code is lost. Yet residents remain anchored in place. In spite of post office departure or a vanished code, the home stands. Attachment to land lingers, rooted deeper than digits."
      "I was initially intrigued by the dilemma of the Postal Service because of the parallel to my own field. Like the letter, the analog photograph seems threatened at present. Digitization has rendered aspects of my own practice obsolete — even entirely extinct. As remains of the analog world coexist with the emergent digital technology, this moment of change begs consideration."
    - Espelie, Erin, 2014; Apple Quicktime video file transferred from external hard drive, approximately 84 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0005)
      Erin Espelie's MFA thesis was a 70-minute film titled The Lanthanide Series.
      Espelie provided the following abstract: "The Lanthanide Series is a poetic experimental documentary that considers the history of black mirrors, the Periodic Table, and rare-earth mining, as related to the progression of imaging technology. The piece is shot almost entirely in reflection of either a defunct tablet or an obsidian disc."
      No restrictions, but please notify the filmmaker via e-mail (erin.espelie@colorado.edu) if the work is used in a classroom or public setting.
    - Garrahan, Sarah, 2014; Apple Quicktime video file transferred from external hard drive, approximately 39 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0006)
      Vida Propia is Sarah Garrahan's 50-minute documentary film. Garrahan provided the following abstract: "Vida Propia chronicles the story of first-generation Mexican immigrant Nora Mendez as she finds herself working in a busy restaurant kitchen in North Carolina and struggling to support her family in the United States. The film's observational style follows Nora through everyday moments -- from working long hours, to spending time with her family, to reflecting upon the meaning of a life narrative itself."
    - Kelly, Caitlin Margaret, 2014, 19 items 1 box 18 black-and-white inkjet prints; 1 postcard 13 x 19 inches